Guide to the Richard L. Watson, Jr. Papers, 1941 - 1989 UA.29.02.0041
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- University, 1947-1988
  - Duke University, History, 1964-65 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Arts Council, 1957-60; 1970-71 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Church Board. Minutes, 1951-53 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Community Chest Campaign, 1948-50 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Community Chest Campaign, 1949-50 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Conference for Secondary School Counselors, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Press, 1971-75 (Box 8)
  - Duke University Press, 1978-79 (Box 8)
  - Duke-UNC National Security Policy Seminar, 1961-66 (Box 8)
  - East Campus-Facilities, 1965 (Box 8)
  - Educational Facilities Committee
    - Sub-Committee on the Gothic Hall Renovation, 1967 (Box 8)
    - Sub-Committee on the Arts Center, 1963-66 (Box 8)
    - Sub-Committee on the Arts Center, Special Committee to Interview Architectural Candidates, 1965-66 (Box 8)
  - Episcopal Student Center, 1959-63 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Advisors, 1952-55 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Adviser, 1955-59 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Club, 1967-73 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Committee on Duke Development Program, 1950-51 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Committee on Parking, 1949-51 (Box 8)
  - Faculty Committee on Selection of President, 1962 (Box 8)
    NOTE: Presidential Selection Files are RESTRICTED.
  - Faculty Committee on Student Concerns, 1969, [2 folders] (Box 8)
  - Faculty Committee on Student Concerns, Background Material, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Faculty-Student Advisory System Committee, 1952-53 (Box 8)
  - Foreign Policy Institute Proposal, 1973-74 (Box 9)
  - Forest History Society, 1981-83 (Box 9)
  - Friends of Duke University Library, 1976-86 (Box 9)
  - Graduate School-Committee on Final Examination Procedures for the M.A. and Ph.D. Degree, 1963-64 (Box 9)
  - Graduate School-Committee on Graduate degree time-limits and fees, 1966-67 (Box 9)
  - Humanities Council, 1967-69 (Box 9)
  - Institute of Policy Studies and Public Affairs
    - 1971-76 (Box 9)
    - Advisory Committee, 1972 (Box 9)
    - Advisory Committee, 1972-75 (Box 9)
    - Advisory Committee, 1973-74 (Box 9)
  - Investment Policies Study Committee, 1974 (Box 9)
  - Joint Faculty-Trustee Committee on Honorary Degrees, 1961-74 (Box 9)
  - Library
    - 1965-85 (Box 9)
    - George Washington Flowers Collection, 1965-72 (Box 9)
    - George Washington Flowers Collection, 1973-83 (Box 9)
    - Special Committee on Gathering Election Material, 1951-52 (Box 9)
    - Library Council, 1947-65 (Box 9)
  - Local 77, 1966 (Box 9)
  - Murphy, Charles (Honorary Degree Recipient), 1967 (Box 9)
  - National Defense Education Act of 1958, Oath and Affidavit, 1959-60 (Box 9)
  - Nixon Honorary Degree Controversy, 1954-57, 1973 (Box 9)
  - Nixon Library
    - Academic Council, 1981 (Box 9)
    - Clippings, 1981-82, [2 folders] (Box 9)
    - Committee Against the Nixon-Duke Library (CANDL), 1981 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, August 1981 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence, September 1981-1982 (Box 9)
    - General, 1981 (Box 9)
    - Watson's Diary and Notes, August-September, 1981 (Box 9)
  - Omicron Delta Kappa, 1953-68 (Box 9)
  - Oral History Project, 1963 (Box 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1977-80 (Box 9)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1981-88 (Box 9)
  - President's Special Advisory Search Committee, 1977-79 (Box 9)
  - Regional Education Laboratory Proposal [also Center for the Study of Higher Education proposal], 1965-66 (Box 10)
  - Social Science Council, 1970-1971 (Box 10)
  - South Atlantic Quarterly, 1972-1988 (Box 10)
  - Student-Faculty-Administration Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 10)
    Includes information on the drug policy, military recruitment on campus, and pickets policy.
  - Student-Faculty-Administration Committee
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Regulations on Pickets, Protests and Demonstrations, 1968-1969 (Box 10)
    - Minutes and Agendas, 1967-1968
      - Military recruiting, 11-27-1967, 12-4-1967 (Box 10)
      - Pickets and Protests, 12-4-1967, 12-14-1967, 12-18-1967, 2-15-1968, 2-22-1968, 3-11-1968, 3-20-1968, 5-6-1968 (Box 10)
      - Drug Policy, 1-9-68, 1-15-1968, 2-15-1968, 2-22-1968, 3-11-1968, 4-5-1968, 4-15-1968 (Box 10)
  - Task Force on Year-Round Operations
    - 1979-80, [3 folders] (Box 10)
    - Draft Reports, 1980 (Box 10)
    - Faculty Concerns Subcommittee, 1980 (Box 10)
  - Traffic Commission, 1952 (Box 10)
  - Traffic Commission, 1955-1956 (Box 10)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Committee of Arts and Sciences, Executive Committee, 1973-1975, [2 folders] (Box 10)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council
    - Committee on Committees, 1965-66 (Box 10)
    - Faculty Committee on Admissions, Minutes, 1952-1953 (Box 10)
    - Sub-Committee on Curriculum, 1970-1971 (Box 10)
    - Report of the Faculty Committee on Admissions, 1953 (Box 10)
  - Review Committee on Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Science (UFCAS) (Box 10)
  - Structure of UFCAS, 1982 (Box 10)
  - Undergraduate Research Assistantship Program, 1976-89 (Box 10)
  - University Admissions Committee, Advisory Committee for Trinity College and College of Engineering, 1963-1965 (Box 10)
  - University Archives, 1955-1978 (Box 10)
  - University Art and History Preservation Committee, 1981 (Box 10)
  - University Arts Center, Report to the Long Range Planning Committee on, 1959 (Box 10)
  - University Council
    - 1957-1962 (Box 10)
      Includes tuition benefits for faculty children.
    - Committee on the By Laws, 1960-1962 (Box 10)
    - Committee to Consider Proposal Concerning Tuition Awards for Faculty Children, 1959 (Box 10)
    - Special Committee on the Future Role of the University Council, 1956 (Box 10)
    - University Committee on Faculty Qualifications and Improvements, 1961 (Box 10)
  - University Planning Committee, Sub-Committee on Regional and State Responsibilities, 1971-1972 (Box 10)
  - University Policy, Planning and Advisory Committee, 1964-66 (Box 10)
  - University Policy, Planning and Advisory Committee, Ad Hoc Committee on the Fifth Decade, 1965 (Box 10)
  - Woman's College Scholarship Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 10)
  - Young Men's Christian Association, Board of Directors, Minutes, 1954-1957, [2 folders] (Box 10)
- Professional Organizations, 1954-1988
  The fourth series, Professional Organizations, documents Watson's long contribution of service to national, state, and local professional historical organizations and his work for the promotion of history. His work with the American Historical Association includes serving on the Ad hoc committee on Ph.D. programs in history, as well as being a session chair and member of the committee to collect the basic data of American political history. For six years he served the Organization of American Historians, and its predecessor organization, the Mississippi Valley Historical Association, as a member of their prize committees. Documents in this series shed light on the changes in prize policy and process. In addition to serving as its president from 1976-1977, Watson served on numerous annual program committees and as session chairs for the Southern Historical Association. This series contains material on program and nominating committees, sessions, and his work on the board of editors of the Journal of Southern History.
  Watson also worked to advance the promotion of history. This series documents his work with the National Historical Publications and Records Commission, the NDEA Institute for Advanced Study in American History, the National Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of History, and the United Negro College Fund Distinguished Scholars Program.
  The series also contains materials related to Watson's work with historical organizations at the state and local level. It documents his twenty-year involvement with the Historical Society of North Carolina, as well as his work with the North Carolina Literary and Historical Association, and the State Archives of North Carolina. At the local level, this series contains materials about the Durham County history project to publish a history of Durham County, N.C.
  - American Historical Association (Box 11)
    - 1977-1985 (Box 11)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Ph.D. Programs in History, 1967-1969, [3 folders] (Box 11)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Ph.D. Programs in History, Program Descriptions, 1969, [4 folders] (Box 11)
    - Committee to Collect the Basic Quantitative Data of American Political History, 1966-1968 (Box 11)
    - Committee to Collect the Basic Quantitative Data of American Political History, North Carolina Election Data, 1964-1966 (Box 11)
    - Session Chair, New Approaches to Recent American Political History, 1961 (Box 11)
  - Appalachian State University, Consultant for M.A. Degree in History, 1967 (Box 11)
  - Dictionary of American Biography, 1974-1975 (Box 11)
    Includes his article on O. Max Gardner
  - Durham County History Project, 1955-64 (Box 11)
  - Durham County History Project, 1965-70 (Box 11)
  - Encyclopedia of Southern History, 1974-76 (Box 11)
  - Ford Foundation, Doctoral Fellowships for Black Students, 1970-72 (Box 11)
    NOTE: Student information is RESTRICTED.
  - Historical Society of North Carolina
    - 1965-69 (Box 11)
    - 1970-72 (Box 11)
    - 1973-75 (Box 11)
    - 1981-87 (Box 11)
    - Committee on a Constitutional Amendment, 1957-58 (Box 11)
  - Indiana Council for the Social Studies, Speaker, 1963-64 (Box 11)
  - Mississippi Valley Historical Association
    - 1962-63 (Box 11)
    - Mississippi Valley Historical Review, Board of Editors, 1958-61 (Box 11)
    - Committee on the Future, 1963-65 (Box 11)
    - Membership Committee, 1962-65 (Box 11)
    - Prize Studies Committee, 1963-65, [2 folders] (Box 11)
    - Prize Studies Committee, Final Appraisals, 1964-65 (Box 11)
      NOTE: Prize appraisals are RESTRICTED.
  - National Coordinating Committee for the Promotion of History, 1976-85 (Box 11)
  - National Council for the Social Studies, 1967-68 (Box 11)
  - National Geographic, 1963-84 (Box 11)
  - National Historical Publications and Records Commission, 1983-89 (Box 11)
  - National Historical Publications and Records Commission, Fellowships in Archival Education, 1985-86 (Box 11)
  - National Defense Education Act (NEDA)
    - Institute for Advanced Study in American History, 1968 (Box 11)
    - Institutes for Advanced Study Evaluation Panel, 1967-68 (Box 12)
    - Summer History Institutes, 1965 (Box 12)
    - Title IV Graduate Fellowship Program, 1967-69 (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Highway Historical Marker Advisory Committee, 1975-79 (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Literary and Historical Association, 1965-67 (Box 12)
  - North Carolina Literary and Historical Association, Mayflower Cup, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Organization of American Historians
    - 1966-73 (Box 12)
    - 1978-88 (Box 12)
    - Committee on Bibliographical and Research Needs, 1974-77 (Box 12)
    - Frederick Jackson Turner Prize Committee
      NOTE: All Turner Prize Committee files are RESTRICTED.
      - 1966-67 (Box 12)
      - 1967-68, [3 folders] (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, 1967-69 (Box 12)
      - Final Appraisals, 1966-67 (Box 12)
      - Manuscript Publication, 1966-67 (Box 12)
      - Submissions, 1966 (Box 12)
      - 1968 (Box 12)
    - Prize Studies Committee
      NOTE: All Prize Studies Committee files are RESTRICTED.
      - 1965-66 (Box 12)
      - 1965-66 (Box 12)
      - Finalists, 1965-66 (Box 12)
      - Submissions, 1965-66 (Box 12)
      - Report of the Prize Study Committee, 1966 (Box 12)
    - Session Chair: "The Progressive Era", 1973-74 (Box 12)
    - Special Committee on Prize Policy, 1965-66 (Box 12)
  - St. Augustine's College, 1984-85 (Box 12)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. University of Houston Accreditation Visit, 1965-66 (Box 12)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Schools. University of Mississippi Accreditation Visit, 1967 (Box 12)
  - Southern Historical Association (Box 13)
    - 1985-86 (Box 13)
    - Board of Editors, Journal of Southern History, 1968-69 (Box 13)
    - Board of Editors, Journal of Southern History, 1970-72 (Box 13)
    - Nominating Committee, 1963 (Box 13)
    - Nominating Committee, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Paper Critique, 1955 (Box 13)
    - Program Committee, 1959-60 (Box 13)
    - Program Committee, 1961-62 (Box 13)
    - Program Committee Chairman, 1963-64 (Box 13)
    - Seminar Paper, "A Political Leader Bolts: F.M. Simmons in the Election of 1928", 1959-61 (Box 13)
    - Session Chair, "Dissent in the New South", 1974 (Box 13)
    - Session Chair, "Harry Truman and the South", 1969 (Box 13)
    - Session Chair, "Southerner Look at the New Deal", 1965 (Box 13)
    - Session Chair, "The Cold War and American Liberalism", 1966 (Box 13)
    - Special Committee to Study the Awards Program, 1966-67 (Box 13)
  - State Archives of North Carolina, 1976-77 (Box 13)
  - Tarheel Junior Historian Association, 1954-55 (Box 13)
  - United Negro College Fund, Distinguished Scholars Program, 1981-89 (Box 13)
  - United Negro College Fund, Distinguished Scholars Program, Scholars-at-Large, 1981-87 (Box 13)
- Research and Writings, ca. 1940-1989
  Forty years of Watson's research and writings are reflected in this fifth series, Research and Writings. The bulk of the series is related to the two major books that Watson edited along with William Cartwright, Interpreting and Teaching American History, and Reinterpretation of American History and Culture. These books were aimed at giving a historiographical overview of American history to high school teachers. Leading scholars of the time contributed essays. The files, which include chapter files and general correspondence, reflect the changes in historiographical interpretations of American history from the early 1960s to the early 1970s. Book reviews, articles, grants and grant applications make up the rest of the series.
  - Articles (Box 14)
    - American Political History, 1900-1920, n.d. (Box 14)
    - Principle, Party, and Constituency: The N.C. Congressional Delegation, 1917-1919, 1978-80 (Box 14)
    - Testing Time for Congressional Leadership: The War Crisis of 1917-18 (Box 14)
    - Woodrow Wilson and His Interpreters, 1947-57, 1957 (Box 14)
  - Bishop Cannon's Own Story (editor), 1955-56 (Box 14)
  - Bishop Cannon's Own Story (editor), Notes and Introduction, ca. 1955 (Box 14)
  - Book Reviews
    - ca. 1940s and 1950s (Box 14)
    - ca. 1950s (Box 14)
    - Roosevelt Letters, 1951 (Box 14)
    - 1959-79 (Box 14)
    - 1980-89 (Box 14)
  - Cannon, James, Encyclopedia Entry, 1960 (Box 14)
  - Grant Applications, 1953-54 (Box 14)
  - Grant Applications, 1957-58 (Box 14)
  - Houghton Mifflin, 1962-79 (Box 14)
  - Interpreting and Teaching American History
    - Biographical Data (Box 14)
    - General Correspondence, 1957-62 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 1 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 2 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 3 File, 1957-60 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 4 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 5 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 6 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 8 File, 1958-60 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 9 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 11 File, 1957-60 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 12 File, 1957-60 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 13 File, 1959-60 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 14 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 16 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 17 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 6 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 15 File, 1957-61 (Box 14)
  - Paper, Theodore Roosevelt and Herbert Hoover: A Study in Political Ideas, n.d. (Box 14)
  - Reinterpretation of American History and Culture
    - General Correspondence, 1970-75 (Box 14)
    - Introduction File, 1971-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 1 File, 1971-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 2 File, 1971-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 3 File, 1970-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 4 File, 1971-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 5 File, 1972-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 6 File, 1971-75 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 7 File, 1971-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 8 File, 1971-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 9 File, 1971-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 10 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 11 File, 1970-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 12 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 13 File, 1970-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 14 File, 1970-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 15 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 16 File, 1970-71 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 17 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 18 File, 1971-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 19 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 20 File, 1970-72 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 21 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 22 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 23 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 24 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
    - Chapter 25 File, 1970-73 (Box 14)
  - University Press of America, 1962, 1975-83 (Box 14)
  - University Research Council Grants, 1949-1987, [4 folders] (Box 14)
- Personal, 1941-1984
  Materials in the sixth series, Personal, relate to Watson's personal activities. They include items about his life in the military, including his military records, correspondence, and a diary from 1944. The series also details his involvement with St. Philip's church of Durham and the Episcopal Church, Diocese of North Carolina. A copy of his curriculum vitae and items related to his retirement and the establishment of the Watson Graduate Fellowship are also included.
  - Allied Arts of Durham, 1966-73 (Box 14)
  - Carolina Charter Corporation, 1964, 1985 (Box 14)
  - Coast Artillery School, 1941-43 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1941-46 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, 1984-85 (Box 14)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1980 (Box 14)
  - Diary, September 29, 1944-December 2, 1944 (Box 14)
  - Episcopal Church, Diocese of North Carolina
    - Commission on Ministry, 1971-76 (Box 14)
    - Sub-Committee on Examinations, Commission on Ministry, 1973-75 (Box 14)
    - Historical Commission, 1959-60 (Box 14)
    - Howard, Noah, 1973-74 (Box 14)
  - Military Records, 1942-55 (Box 14)
  - Northfield Mount Hermon School, 1960-69 (Box 14)
  - Operation Breakthrough (Durham), 1969 (Box 14)
  - Retirement and Watson Graduate Fellowship, 1983-84 (Box 14)
  - St. Philip's Church, 1960-67 (Box 14)
  - St. Philip's Church, 1964-71 (Box 14)
  - St. Philip's Church, Rector, 1967 (Box 14)
  - United Durham, Inc., ca. 1971-74 (Box 14)
  - Yale University, 1955, 1972-78 (Box 14)